<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="2.5.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-16T13:02:31-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Missing Maps</title><entry xml:lang="en"><title>OSM Geography Awareness Week: 13-19 November</title><link href="/blog/2016/10/07/osm-geoweek/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OSM Geography Awareness Week: 13-19 November" /><published>2016-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/10/07/osm-geoweek</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/10/07/osm-geoweek/">&lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap Geography Awareness Week –or OSM GeoWeek, as we call it– is taking place from 13-19 November, and Missing Maps members are gearing up to support a variety of events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each November, OSM GeoWeek serves as a time when teachers, students, community groups, organizations, and map lovers around the world join together to celebrate geography and make maps with OpenStreetMap, the free and openly editable map of the world. GeoWeek activities include both mapathons and field-based mapping activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-back--looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking back / looking forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year the Missing Maps members supported &lt;strong&gt;94 events in 32 countries&lt;/strong&gt;, and we can’t wait to see what the community can accomplish this year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Red Cross GIS team has started planning with the Missing Maps member organizations in the US and Europe, as well as with our colleagues in DC at the Peace Corps, MapGive, OFDA, HIU, and local universities. We’ll be reaching out directly to a number of universities and organizations in the hopes that they’ll be interested in hosting a mapping event during GeoWeek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week presents a great opportunity for students, coworkers, or members of a community organization to participate in something both meaningful and fun this fall. Participants don’t need any expertise, just basic computer skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get involved!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your organization is interested in participating, the Missing Maps network and our colleagues can provide you with the information and materials needed to host a successful mapathon. If you’re located in the USA, then we can even send you a box of stickers and other swag as a care package for your event! If you’d like to host an event, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1SG9DW7ZyEC9Vf78RbApUfBYAQPSIReyxbupGJPCqjtw/viewform?edit_requested=true&quot;&gt;sign up here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20161007_swag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stickers galore&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Want some stylish mapathon accessories for your event? Sign up on the website and we'll mail you a box of stickers and more! (Apologies to those outside the USA, but we can't ship internationally)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Eros</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="GeoWeek" /><category term="Mapathons" /><category term="OSM" /><summary>Missing Maps members are gearing up for OSM Geography Awareness Week this Novmber, hoping to support over 100 mapathons around the world!</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>Putting Guinea’s reproductive health issues on the map</title><link href="/blog/2016/09/16/guinea-women/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Putting Guinea’s reproductive health issues on the map" /><published>2016-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/09/16/guinea-women</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/09/16/guinea-women/">&lt;p&gt;The Missing Maps project aims to put the world’s most vulnerable people on the map. There can be few people more vulnerable than a woman in childbirth and her unborn baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish, Swiss and British Red Cross are currently working together to support the Guinea Red Cross in developing integrated, high quality programmes, and the Reproductive Health and Rights Programme is one of these. It aims to improve knowledge and access to reproductive health and rights in the Moyenne Guinée region of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of Missing Maps within the context of the programme is to provide the detailed basemaps with which programme staff can effectively carry out a baseline survey to better understand the barriers that exist to accessing reproductive health services, and the prevalence of harmful practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accurate basemaps will also allow for more effective strategic planning around the provision of training and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guinea--a-country-living-and-dying-with-the-effects-of-fgm&quot;&gt;Guinea – A country living and dying with the effects of FGM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the West African country of Guinea had the 18th highest maternal mortality rate in the world – 679 deaths in pregnancy or childbirth per 100,000 live births, according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.STA.MMRT/countries/GN?display=default&quot;&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; from the World Health Organisation (WHO). For purposes of comparison, the number for the UK is 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most significant contributing factors in this high number of deaths is the prevalence of female genital mutilation in the country. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unicef.org/media/files/UNICEF_FGM_report_July_2013_Hi_res.pdf&quot;&gt;According to UNICEF&lt;/a&gt;, 96% of women in Guinea have undergone FGM – the second highest rate in the world, behind only Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2016, the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights said that, “Although female genital mutilation appears to be decreasing worldwide, this is not the case in Guinea, where this practice is widespread in every region and among every ethnic, religious and social group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risk-rural-areas-and-remote-mapping&quot;&gt;Risk, rural areas and remote mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this widespread practice, many Guinean women are at high risk of suffering complications during childbirth. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2006/pr30/en/&quot;&gt;WHO&lt;/a&gt;, certain types of FGM result in an approximately 30% increase in the need for caesarean section, and a 70% increase in incidents of severe blood loss after giving birth. There is also a 15-55% increase in death rates for babies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its analysis of global maternal mortality rates meanwhile, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs348/en/&quot;&gt;WHO reported&lt;/a&gt; that, “Most maternal deaths are preventable, as the health-care solutions to prevent or manage complications are well known.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also found that, “poor women in remote areas are the least likely to receive adequate health care,” with poverty, distance, lack of information, inadequate services and cultural practices all being key factors in the reasons for pregnant women not receiving the essential emergency care they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;helping-to-prevent-the-preventable&quot;&gt;Helping to prevent the preventable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tackle these issues, the Guinea Red Cross’ Reproductive Health and Rights Programme, aims in part to improve access to emergency medical care for women experiencing childbirth complications. It also aims to shift practices and cultural viewpoints regarding FGM, and to improve knowledge, rights and access to reproductive health in key areas of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160916_village.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;village&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Community in Labé region. CC-BY-NC-ND British Red Cross, Danish Red Cross and Swiss Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme has been ongoing for several years, with the support of the Swiss and Danish Red Cross, and recently the British Red Cross joined the partnership as it enters a new phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for this new phase of the project to get underway, a ‘baseline survey’ needs to be carried out to establish current levels of access and knowledge across six sub-prefectures. It will also be necessary to collect data in order to measure change as the project progresses, and upon its conclusion. And that’s where Missing Maps comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-mammoth-mapping-task&quot;&gt;A mammoth mapping task&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the baseline survey could take place, accurate base maps were needed of each area, and these were non-existent. So to carry out the extensive amount of mapping required in a relatively short space of time, the British Red Cross maps team in London turned to the Missing Maps project and Humanitarian OpenStreetmap Team (HOT) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team uploaded three projects to the HOT Tasking Manager, with instructions for volunteers to map roads, residential areas, buildings and other geographic features. Each project covered two sub-prefectures, and together covered a mammoth area of 777 square miles – almost 1.3 times the size of Greater London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In less than two months, all six sub-prefectures have been mapped - an impressive feat, and a testament to the incredible impact that the Missing Maps community can have when it works together. In just the six study areas – remote volunteers mapped 40,734 buildings and 1283 residential areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sous-Prefecture&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Dionfo&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tangali&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bodie&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mafara&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Maci&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Ninguelande&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Total&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Buildings&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3435&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3056&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8370&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7754&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7972&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10147&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40734&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Residential Areas&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;188&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;211&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;315&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;219&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;260&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1283&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the map features added by remote Missing Maps volunteers have been validated for accuracy, it will be combined with GPS data on village names and other local information collected as part of the baseline survey, creating a rich basemap that is accessible in OpenStreetMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The completed maps will then be available for project staff and volunteers to use throughout the programme, and will provide a vital geographic data source with which to visualise the results from the baseline survey.  More importantly, they will play an integral role in implementing systems which will help to ensure that pregnant women experiencing birth complications get the immediate medical attention they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160916_dwelling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dwelling&quot; style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Baseline surveying. CC-BY-NC-ND British Red Cross, Danish Red Cross and Swiss Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without accurate maps – which can guide to a destination, highlight needs, reveal patterns and track developments - the work of aid and development organisations to save and enhance lives can be made even more difficult. Through the efforts of HOT and the Missing Maps community, large swathes of the world which were previously in shadow have been revealed, and the positive impacts of this are only just beginning to be realised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160916_team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;team&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The mobile data collection team. CC-BY-NC-ND British Red Cross, Danish Red Cross and Swiss Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Glithero, Paul Knight, Kat Hicks</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="Field Mapping" /><category term="Guinea" /><category term="Mobile Data Collection" /><summary>The Danish, Swiss and British Red Cross are currently working together to support the Guinea Red Cross in developing integrated, high quality programmes, and the Reproductive Health and Rights Programme is one of these. It aims to improve knowledge and access to reproductive health and rights in the Moyenne Guinée region of the country.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>Mapping Every Detail</title><link href="/blog/2016/08/02/mapping-every-detail/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping Every Detail" /><published>2016-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/08/02/mapping-every-detail</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/08/02/mapping-every-detail/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;emerging-cities&quot;&gt;Emerging cities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘city’ often elicits an image of towering metropolises. However, this image is more consistent with cities found in already developed nations. For the many towns and evolving communities in still developing countries, we have a different classification: ‘emerging cities’. These emerging cities are at the center of development, showing rapid population growth as an increasing number of people leave villages to pursue opportunity in these cities. In these epicenters of commerce, a wide range of commodities can be found in markets as people innovate and continue to improve their livelihoods. In all of this, we see promise as humanity advances and lives and communities continue to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160802_city.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Emerging cities, emerging promise.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Emerging cities, emerging promise. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-map&quot;&gt;Why map?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These emerging cities are bustling hubs of activity: services deliver and transport goods, factories create products, government institutions and various NGO’s reach out and work to create development programs that benefit the community. Schools, health facilities and markets serve as hosts for residents of neighboring communities and villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In West Africa, these emerging cities are spread everywhere. Their population is increasing and they are growing. One thing is similar across all of them, nothing or not much is mapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After initially sending volunteers to record all the population centres in the border regions, we then selected some emerging cities in Liberia, Guinea and Sierra Leone to map in their entirety. Volunteers spend hours and days moving from one corner of the city to the other mapping every mappable entity, capturing every detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping these expanding cities provides more precise information on the whereabouts of services and amenities like police stations, theaters, hospitals and hotels. When I was in Kenema City, Sierra Leone I just wanted to go to a particular hotel. It took me several stops at various corners of the city asking for the location but no one I asked knew and it had not yet been mapped into OpenStreetMap. By creating an open repository of geographic data, we are working to establish a more complete and reliable resource that will prevent more experiences like the one I had in Kenema City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping these cities can have a greater effect than just improved information about the location of buildings and services. Just recovering from the worst disease outbreak of recent history, Liberia, Guinea and Sierra Leone are picking themselves up and preparing to better deal with future disasters. Mapping the emerging cities in West Africa and the surrounding region is a relevant and vital part of this preparedness. Mapping the infrastructure in emerging cities can help immensely in disaster response situations. Because diseases outbreaks are a disaster that has a high potential to spread across international borders and destabilize economies, mapping these cities and regions carries an even greater importance than previously realized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-city-at-the-center-of-the-outbreak&quot;&gt;A city at the center of the outbreak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in the south of Guinea, the city of Gueckedou is one of the major gateways to the country. Decades ago it was known for its international weekly market every Wednesday. Vendors and buyers would start arriving a day before in preparation for the millions of Guinean Francs that would change hands. It attracted traders from Côte d’Ivoire, Senegal, Mali, Liberia and Sierra Leone. Traded goods were even taken on to Conakry, the capital city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160802_market.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Market day in Gueckedou&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Market day in Gueckedou. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wars of Liberia and Sierra Leone reached the beautiful city and changed the story. For a time, rebels and the Guinea military battled in the city, but eventually the violence ended and life returned to normal. Then in December 2013 the first death from Ebola occurred and still other deaths followed. At that time the city was not mapped, so Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team volunteers and others traced the buildings and roads in the region in response to the crisis. The data was crucially important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By 7:00pm, the entire city would almost be deserted. It was death in the city.” Bayo, a former volunteer with MSF narrates to me, “My colleagues and I would move to many place and it was always the same, a state of fear and uncertainty. One of our volunteer colleagues lost the battle to Ebola as did many other people. But this one was particularly painful to me because we were out there saving lives, I don’t know what went wrong on a particular day and he got the virus. He couldn’t make it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He continues, “If any one became sick in that time, your family would desert you. I remember suffering from typhoid in that period, and every one at home thought it was Ebola, it was a very hard time being rejected and isolated by my own family. Access to the villages for contact tracing, treating the sick or for burial was hard due to the nature of the roads. Worse still, it was hard to navigate to some of these places without a map, especially in the beginning phases. But later on, we got maps and it was easier to find the villages.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-ahead&quot;&gt;Looking ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Celestine Kamano is one of our Field Team Leaders in Guinea. Despite being a recent graduate in Linguistic Science, Celestine has been using his brother’s laptop to learn to map whenever he is not in the field collecting data. When our work started he had not found a job yet. Hte was successful in applying for and joining our team. Now he is thinking of changing his career to better contribute to his country through mapping. “I am saving up to buy a laptop so that I can always be able to map my country. This project has opened my eyes. There are a lot of things not mapped here, and now I know that I can make a contribution to my country by mapping. Through going to very many communities within the 15 kilometre radius, I have seen how life is from community to community. This has given me a lot of reflection on what my country and communities are. I am already thinking of how I can help; I will start with mapping.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160802_celestine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Celestine mapping&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Celestine mapping. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, a project manager for another of the projects going on in Gueckedou was thanking us at the Mapping Hub for reducing his burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one town, after explaining why we are mapping and how useful it is, a lady came running after our volunteers to ask that her house be mapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another community, while mapping was going on, we took time to view submissions to the server to show the volunteers real time results from their efforts. The volunteers were with a local leader from this community, and as we started viewing the uploads and the mapped buildings, a group of young men came as well to steal a look. Judging by their enthusiastic looks at our work, those young men are potential mappers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160802_server.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Viewing submissions&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Viewing submissions to the server in the field. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stories are true for many other cities and places across Africa. Mapping is integral to the development of nations of the world, and the local knowledge of communities that is necessary to mapping is best provided by people who live and stay in those places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that the importance of this mapped data is not limited to disaster response. With it, nations and governments can better understand the problems and challenges facing them and use this information to make steps towards prevailing over those challenges. There is tremendous power in knowledge, which is acquired through analysis of gathered data. In this case, governments, organizations, and civil society are benefiting from a tremendous volume of relevant data gathered by the local population and stored in a place accessible by anybody – OpenStreetMap.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Luswata</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="Field Mapping" /><category term="West Africa" /><category term="Ebola" /><category term="MSF" /><summary>After initially sending volunteers to record all the population centres in the border regions, we then selected some emerging cities in Liberia, Guinea and Sierra Leone to map in their entirety. Volunteers spend hours and days moving from one corner of the city to the other mapping every mappable entity, capturing every detail.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>What’s new with MapSwipe</title><link href="/blog/2016/08/01/mapswipe-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What's new with MapSwipe" /><published>2016-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/08/01/mapswipe-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/08/01/mapswipe-update/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-the-latest-mapswipe-update-and-you-will-find-a-whole-load-of-improvements&quot;&gt;Get the latest MapSwipe update and you will find a whole load of improvements!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/blog/2016/07/22/mapswipe-progress-and-feedback/&quot;&gt;the excellent feedback so many of you sent us&lt;/a&gt;, our team has been hard at work to get the next &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapswipe.org/&quot;&gt;MapSwipe&lt;/a&gt; update out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge was that of &lt;strong&gt;repeated imagery&lt;/strong&gt;. Previously, you probably had suspicions that you were mapping the same areas over and over again. Unfortunately, you were right. This was due to a bug in the distribution algorithm and is now fixed. You should now be mapping in new areas every time you charge up the app! One sad consequence of this is that, while projects looked like they were finished, not all the areas within them had been mapped. As a result , you will notice that the completion rates on some missions on the homescreen have dropped significantly. Although this looks like a negative outcome, what it actrually means is that we will get through projects much faster now, as you guys cover a wider area more efficiently. So, keep mapping! Those percentages will fly up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you experienced &lt;strong&gt;perpetual loading screens&lt;/strong&gt; in certain missions and this has also been fixed. However, if you do experience either repeated imagery or perpetual loading, we have added another button to each mission screen called &lt;em&gt;Bugs? Clear project data&lt;/em&gt;. Hitting this button should reset your data for that particular mission, meaning these issues should no longer exist…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt; was flagged as lacking within MapSwipe. While most of you are enjoying the the usability of the app, many of you wanted more help understanding exactly what you were being asked to identify. You should now see a &lt;em&gt;Tutorial&lt;/em&gt; button in each mission which will take you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/blog/2016/07/18/mapswipetutorial/&quot;&gt;to this blog post&lt;/a&gt;. We will be working to improve the blog post itself over the next few days as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe5-LIScH0URlymhTzXAyrbTJUEMmfBvWfBVuW38Zw9PnxPzA/viewform?c=0&amp;amp;w=1&quot;&gt;Your feedback is always welcome&lt;/a&gt; to help us make this better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/thumb/2/2e/MSSS11.JPG/344px-MSSS11.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;New features&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New features on the mission pages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, there are a few other small usability tweaks that should make your MapSwiping faster and smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that you enjoy these changes… We are still working on &lt;strong&gt;open sourcing the code&lt;/strong&gt; via github and developing an &lt;strong&gt;exporter&lt;/strong&gt;, so you can download and use the data as well as contributing to it. Watch this space for more news…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also like to provide MapSwipe information in &lt;strong&gt;languages other than English&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’d like to contribute to this, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1rWkOUze6GTagZDnKEENdYxGjlOaAC1PUL0AvoHxBSY0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;there is a shared spreadsheet here&lt;/a&gt;. Please feel free to add the name of your language to the column header and translate the highlighted cells. We will add new languages into the app in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your feedback and bug reports are still more than welcome, via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe5-LIScH0URlymhTzXAyrbTJUEMmfBvWfBVuW38Zw9PnxPzA/viewform?c=0&amp;amp;w=1&quot;&gt;feedback form&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapswipe/app-feedback/issues&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you all for helping us make MapSwipe fly! We are so pleased that so many of you are choosing to help humaniatarian organisations by MapSwiping the areas in which they are providing for vulnerable communities. Keep up the great work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pete Masters</name></author><category term="[&quot;MapSwipe&quot;]" /><category term="MSF" /><category term="Tech" /><summary>Following the excellent feedback so many of you sent us, our team has been hard at work to get the next update out. Get the details, here!</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>MapSwipe… Feeding back on your feedback</title><link href="/blog/2016/07/22/mapswipe-progress-and-feedback/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MapSwipe... Feeding back on your feedback" /><published>2016-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/07/22/mapswipe-progress-and-feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/07/22/mapswipe-progress-and-feedback/">&lt;p&gt;So, your response to &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapswipe.org/&quot;&gt;MapSwipe&lt;/a&gt; has been phenomenal, already!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 5,000 users are already helping us to put vulnerable communities on the map, so NGOs and local organisations can better reach them with medical care and humanitarian assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/thumb/2/2e/Mapswipe_lockup_blackclear.png/640px-Mapswipe_lockup_blackclear.png&quot; alt=&quot;MapSwipe logo&quot; href=&quot;http://mapswipe.org/&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also had an amazing response in terms of feedback and bug reports. This is vital for us to be able to prioritise where we put our efforts going forward with MapSwipe. I want to address the most common of these feedbacks, but also invite everyone to let us know what you think. There are two ways of leaving feedback and reporting bugs. The first is via &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/MapSwipeFBack&quot;&gt;this feedback form&lt;/a&gt; and the second is via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapswipe/app-feedback/issues&quot;&gt;the MapSwipe github&lt;/a&gt; (more on this below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;repeating-satellite-imagery&quot;&gt;Repeating satellite imagery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people are reporting that they MapSwipe the same images more than once. This is happening. The reason is that the algorithm chooses the least mapped image for you to work on. As so many people are mapping at once, you will sometimes get this area more than once. Do not worry, this does not mean no-one else is mapping this area. We are working to fix this now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lack-of-guidance--tutorials&quot;&gt;Lack of guidance / tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many users have asked for more in the way of guidance. This relates to what to look for and how to spot it, rather than how to use the app technically. As soon as we found out that you felt this was lacking, we put together a tutorial on the Missing Maps blog. As nearly a thousand people have already been to read it, we see that it is needed! We will integrate it better into the app itself as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-code-on-the-github&quot;&gt;No code on the GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true. It won’t be for long - it’s near the top of the to-do list! We will also be making the app available via the apk for those that don’t use google or iOS app stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;progress-bars-are-stuck-on-the-individual-missions&quot;&gt;Progress bars are stuck on the individual missions.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes they are. This is being fixed now. And, don’t worry - the data is safe! Keep mapping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;languages-other-than-english&quot;&gt;Languages other than English&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologies for this, but at the moment we don’t have the capacity for supporting multiple languages. Huge thanks to all that have offered to translate. Watch this space for news on this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please keep in mind that this application is brand new, and we understand that it is not yet polished. We’re working as hard as we can to make the experience smoother, so please don’t get discouraged if it doesn’t work quite like it ought to (and please keep submitting those bug reports)!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to leave you with an excellent MapSwipe video made by Map Men. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mwRdtnfFcUw&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img.youtube.com/vi/mwRdtnfFcUw/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MapSwipe by Map Men&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pete Masters</name></author><category term="[&quot;MapSwipe&quot;]" /><category term="MSF" /><category term="Tech" /><summary>We have had an amazing response to MapSwipe in terms of the mapping you have done, but also your feedback and bug reports. We are listening! Find out here what we are doing to address the most common issues.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>MapSwipe Tutorial</title><link href="/blog/2016/07/18/mapswipetutorial/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MapSwipe Tutorial" /><published>2016-07-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/07/18/mapswipetutorial</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/07/18/mapswipetutorial/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;mapswipe-how-to-map-from-the-satellite-imagery&quot;&gt;MapSwipe: How to map from the satellite imagery!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, thank you so much for contributing to the Missing Maps project via &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapswipe.org&quot;&gt;MapSwipe&lt;/a&gt;. We are blown away by your response so far!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you have been in touch to give your comments, suggestions and bug reports. We’d like to try and address one of the main requests: guidance on mapping from the satellite imagery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MapSwipe pro tip - did you know if you hold down a tile it will zoom so that you see it more carefully?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping is never straightforward. Buildings and roads differ hugely from country to country. This blog post aims to give some examples but is by no means comprehensive. In the future, we also hope to build training and support into the app. Please feel free to keep your feedback coming!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be looking at imagery from the Niger State (Nigeria) missions for the following items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buildings&quot;&gt;Buildings:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;two main types of building in this area; rectangular structures with metal or wooden roofs and round huts with roofs of straw&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/e/e2/MSSS3.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Building examples&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Building examples&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rectangular buildings are much easier to spot as they are generally square and usually fairly large. The round huts, however, are often smaller and blend more into the landscape. You can see the differences in the examples below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/8/82/MSSS1.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Rectangular buildings&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Rectangular buildings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;round huts can&lt;/strong&gt; be differentiated from natural features, such as trees and rocks because they usually appear to be a (near-perfect) circle. They are also often grouped together into villages or hamlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/5/51/MSSS2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Round huts&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Round huts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very important that we try and identify all structures in this task, so take your time when swiping and look out for these groups of shapes. &lt;strong&gt;Remember, if you are unsure you can always tap it twice to turn the tile yellow indicating “maybe”.&lt;/strong&gt; It is often better to be on the safe side and tap to indicate a feature as other mappers will review and map the areas you have identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;roads&quot;&gt;Roads:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Road and tracks are sometimes easy to see and sometimes very faint in the satellite imagery. Major roads are usually obvious, but the smaller paths can be tricky to identify. Many people have asked whether we want them to map just major roads or paths and tracks as well. Unfortunately, it is not that simple!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/c/c4/MSSS4.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Road example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Road example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we need is the &lt;strong&gt;road networks&lt;/strong&gt;. This will always include well-established roads. Does it include tracks and paths? Sometimes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/2/28/MSSS5.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Road and path examples&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Road and path examples&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a &lt;strong&gt;track or a path&lt;/strong&gt; leads to a village or hamlet (or to a larger road), we need to know where it is. If it leads to a field, it is not necessary to map. However, because you only have a limited view of the area, it is often difficult to tell. It’s a good idea to swipe left and right to see if you can see where the path or track goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/2/20/MSSS6.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Dead end path examples&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Dead end path examples&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where you see that a track or path ends before hitting a village, hamlet or another road, please ignore it. Otherwise, please identify it. &lt;strong&gt;Remember, if you are unsure you can always tap it twice to turn the tile yellow indicating “maybe”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rivers-and-river-beds&quot;&gt;Rivers and river beds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example above, you can see there is a &lt;strong&gt;dry riverbed&lt;/strong&gt;. We are not generally asking for waterways to be mapped in these tasks, but &lt;strong&gt;it looks like this one is also used as a path&lt;/strong&gt;, so we would ask for it to be mapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/a/ae/MSSS7.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;River bed example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;River bed example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, you can identify a river because they meander, whereas roads tend to go straight from one place to another. Swipe left and right to see how the feature moves if you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are unsure of anything, it might be best to double tap the area to indicate a possible feature as other mappers will come later to map the areas you have identified and they will be able to check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bad-imagery-and-clouds&quot;&gt;Bad imagery and clouds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By triple tapping on a square turning the tile red, you can indicate that you cannot see the landscape. This could be because you have encountered &lt;strong&gt;an absence of imagery, poor quality imagery or clouds&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘'’camera icon’’’ in the first example means there is no imagery available for this area. Triple tapping here is important because it lets us know where we need to find alternative sources for imagery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/c/ce/MSSS8.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Missing imagery example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Missing imagery example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second example, you would triple tap because the cloud is obscuring your view of the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/c/c9/MSSS9.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Cloudy imagery example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cloudy imagery example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the third example, there is a little cloud, but you can see clearly that there is nothing underneath it, so you can swipe this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/9/92/MSSS10.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Cloudy imagery example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cloudy imagery example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-finally&quot;&gt;And, finally…!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope this is a useful resource for you. Please feel free to share it so others may also benefit. If you have any feedback on this or any other aspects of MapSwipe, please feel free to use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe5-LIScH0URlymhTzXAyrbTJUEMmfBvWfBVuW38Zw9PnxPzA/viewform?c=0&amp;amp;w=1&quot;&gt;feedback form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, remember that no one person is responsible for any area. Multiple people look at every tile. If you miss something, others might see it. Although, obviously, please try not to miss anything ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks again for helping humanitarians…..&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pete Masters</name></author><category term="[&quot;MapSwipe&quot;]" /><category term="MSF" /><category term="Tech" /><summary>MapSwipe relies on users being able to interpret what they see in the satellite imagery provided. This tutorial gives some guidance on how best to do that.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>MapSwipe</title><link href="/blog/2016/07/14/mapswipe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MapSwipe" /><published>2016-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/07/14/mapswipe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/07/14/mapswipe/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;mapswipe-with-every-swipe-and-tap-you-help-put-families-on-the-map&quot;&gt;MapSwipe: With every swipe and tap, you help put families on the map&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Downloading &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapswipe.org/&quot;&gt;MapSwipe&lt;/a&gt; means that in a matter of minutes you can contribute to the work being done around the world by MSF, the Red Cross and others, and all from the comfort of your own phone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/thumb/d/dc/DSC_0355.JPG/640px-DSC_0355.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Using MapSwipe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Using MapSwipe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a humanitarian crisis, the location of the most vulnerable people is fundamental information for delivering food, shelter, medical care and other services where they are most needed. And, although it may be hard to believe, millions people around the world are not represented on any accessible map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/&quot;&gt;Missing Maps project&lt;/a&gt;, MapSwipe enables anyone with a smartphone to contribute to the mapping of these vulnerable communities. &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapswipe.org/&quot;&gt;Download the app&lt;/a&gt;, choose a mission, read the instructions and get started! One tap identifies features, a second tap indicates possible features (if you’re not sure) and a third  flags cloudy or bad quality imagery areas.  If there is nothing to identify, just swipe to the next image! You can download imagery for offline MapSwiping on an underground train or plane, so say goodbye to your wasted commuter hours on Candy Crush or Angry Birds!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/thumb/1/14/Mapswipe_screens.PNG/640px-Mapswipe_screens.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots from MapSwipe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Screenshots from MapSwipe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.msf.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Medecins Sans Frontieres / Doctors Without Borders (MSF)&lt;/a&gt;, MapSwipe serves a direct purpose for NGOs. For example, when MSF responds to major disease outbreaks with mass vaccination campaigns, hundreds of teams have to cover enormous areas (as in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.msf.org.uk/article/democratic-republic-of-congo-measles-an-epidemic-emergency&quot;&gt;measles outbreak in Democratic Republic of Congo last year&lt;/a&gt;). Now, with MapSwipe, we can give vaccination campaign coordinators a super-fast snapshot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.msf.org.uk/article/drc-saving-lives-with-remote-mapping&quot;&gt;where the population clusters are&lt;/a&gt;, helping them to send their teams to the locations where they are most needed to achieve maximum vaccination coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Missing Maps project is a collaborative project in which a large and committed community of NGOs, academic institutes, companies and most of all individual mappers map vulnerable areas in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;. By using MapSwipe to identify where communities are located, you also give these mappers the ability to use their talents to map the towns and villages in these areas without having to search through miles of jungle and bush to find them, saving time and helping to put valuable data into the hands of field teams even faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, get the app. Tell your friends. And, let us know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy mapping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/w/images/thumb/2/2e/Mapswipe_lockup_blackclear.png/640px-Mapswipe_lockup_blackclear.png&quot; alt=&quot;MapSwipe logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NB. The satellite imagery we use is generously provided by Bing / Microsoft Corporation (who also make a huge amount of imagery available for OpenStreetMap). Unfortunately, a bug in the MapSwipe app currently prevents us from displaying attribution appropriately. We are working to get this fixed!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pete Masters</name></author><category term="[&quot;MapSwipe&quot;]" /><category term="MSF" /><category term="Tech" /><category term="MapSwipe" /><summary>MapSwipe enables anyone with a smartphone to contribute to the mapping of these vulnerable communities. Download the app, choose a mission, read the instructions and get started!</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>Trends of Transformation by Mapping in West Africa</title><link href="/blog/2016/07/11/trends-of-transformation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trends of Transformation by Mapping in West Africa" /><published>2016-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/07/11/trends-of-transformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/07/11/trends-of-transformation/">&lt;p&gt;Sierra Leone. Liberia. Guinea. Driving from one capital to another, from one end of the border to the other, I cannot help but notice that the last 27 years have been particularly difficult for life in these three greatly endowed countries. They form what is known as the Mano River Union (MRU). In 1989, the First Liberian Civil broke out, hundreds of thousands of lives were lost. Not long after this war started, in 1991 the Sierra Leone Civil war broke out. In 1997, it was thought that life had come back to normal in Liberia, but just two years later, backed by neighboring Guinea, the Second Liberia Civil war broke out. The impact and effects of each of these wars spilled so easily over to each one of its neighboring Mano River Union comrades. War drums have since 2003 been terminated, with a sincere living hope, that they will never sound again, ever. Moving through the border regions of the great countries, I easily notice the pain and impact the times of war have caused to the lives in these three countries. You so easily see houses, very well constructed, abandoned in the bushes no longer habited. Where are the inhabitants… do not ask that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160711_abandoned-house.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Abandoned house&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Abandoned house. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greatly endowed with the Atlantic Ocean, very many rivers, thick forests and great diamond and other mineral deposits, “Life has since then been on an upward scale. Every one going about their business, building a nation and a region again,” narrates my driver as we cruise through the potholed roads of Macenta Prefecture in Guinea on our way to Liberia. “It was so until something strange came among us. We had fought many battles, but this was to be different. We were fighting an enemy we could not see. We didn’t know where he came from, we had never heard or seen something like that.” he continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160711_osmand.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Navigating&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Navigation using [OsmAnd](http://osmand.net/). CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is called the Ebola Virus Disease (EVD). It’s one of the strangest disease outbreaks of recent history. As it were, a single case can turn into a full brown outbreak with in just days, if unknown or left unchecked. In 2014, in a small village in Guinea, it was thought to be a normal death, within weeks, it spread like a spirited fire. Spread across to Liberia and Sierra Leone and many other places. Life was extremely unbearable. As weeks went by, there was an increasing somber feeling sweeping across the region, people were dying. This outbreak was another great threat to the region. In January, March and June 2016, WHO declared the end of the EVD outbreak in Liberia, Sierra Leone and Guinea respectively. However, individuals departing and entering any of these countries are required to take temperature readings. This is still happening as well at all border crossings in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160711_taking-temperature.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Safety precautions&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Getting a temperature reading at a border crossing. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work in the recent couple of months has been to map communities in a 15Km buffer of the three countries’ borders – this was the region most affected by EVD. This has been achieved over and above our expectation. Each of these countries has had its challenges in mapping the communities, but the successes supersede the somewhat expected challenges. The border area forms an interior part of the three countries, with thick forests in most parts, many rivers and several types of wild animals. Roads are in indeed poorer conditions in these border areas, telecommunication signals unavailable in a vast part of the region and socio-economic facilities and services far-fetched in majority of the places. The power of volunteerism still reaches even to the very remotes village. Equipped with a mobile phone, &lt;a href=&quot;http://openmapkit.org/&quot;&gt;OMK&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/&quot;&gt;ODK&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://osmand.net/&quot;&gt;OsmAnd&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://opensignal.com/&quot;&gt;OpenSignal&lt;/a&gt;, we sent volunteers to as many communities as people live in. Some places, a motorbike can’t reach, you have to walk for some hours to get to a community, or in some, grab a boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160711_volunteer-travel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Volunteer travel&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Travel by motorbike and foot may be the only way to reach some communities. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some volunteers not owning a smart phone, tests were done and the best volunteers were selected. With the excitement of the new tools to use, volunteers spread out to the entire region, first in Liberia, then Guinea and then Sierra Leone. Having lost several relatives and community members in the epidemic, the stories of these energetic and passionate volunteers drive me to map one more village, and want to teach whoever I can reach how to map. Many of them participated in contact tracing and community sensitization during the pandemic. Building on these basic tech skills, we are building a community that will continue to map these countries, putting the world’s most vulnerable people on the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160711_volunteer-mapping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Volunteer mapping&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A volunteer gathering data from community members. CC-BY David Luswata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most rewarding moments is when volunteers ask to have these tools on their personal phones. They continue to frequent the Hub eager to take part in all that may be available. We are looking forward to having many hang around the Hub, analyzing and cleaning the data they having been collecting, and learning how to submit it and how to make edits to OpenStreetMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mapping of many of these communities, and other parts of the region in West Africa is making valuable data available to governments, different development partners and the local population, thus guiding and informing the trends of transformation in the region.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Luswata</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="Field Mapping" /><category term="West Africa" /><category term="Ebola" /><summary>Our work in the recent couple of months has been to map communities in a 15 kilometre buffer of the borders of Sierra Leone, Liberia and Guinea – this was the region most affected by Ebola Virus Disease. This has been achieved over and above our expectation. Each of these countries has had its challenges in mapping the communities, but the successes supersede the somewhat expected challenges.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>Atom Feed</title><link href="/blog/2016/07/06/atomfeed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atom Feed" /><published>2016-07-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/07/06/atomfeed</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/07/06/atomfeed/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;subscribe-to-the-blog&quot;&gt;Subscribe to the blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the year 2016 atom feeds are still very useful so we’ve added an atom feed to our blog. You can now subscribe to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://missingmaps.org/feed.xml&quot;&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt; and get the latest updates on Missing Maps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dale Kunce</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Website" /><category term="Tech" /><summary>As the blog expands we added an atom feed so you can subscribe and get the latest updates on Missing Maps.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title>Without Frontiers in Border Country</title><link href="/blog/2016/06/28/border-country/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Without Frontiers in Border Country" /><published>2016-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/06/28/border-country</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/06/28/border-country/">&lt;p&gt;‘Kondewakoro…’. I say it out-loud without meaning to. The young lad responds in Krio. Ahmet translates, although I’m starting to understand Krio. It is what I thought: ‘He says still three hours. 16 kilometers.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t have time. We have to turn back, but if I’ve got it wrong, there will be nowhere to stay back where we came from either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kondewakoro is a border village in the far reaches of the Toli Chiefdom of Kono District, Sierra Leone. AKA ‘Diamond Country’. On &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=7/8.500/-11.541&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, the only map of this corner of Africa, the road we are on shows as a decently defined yellow line. In England or Wales, it would be a tarmacced trunk road. We are not on tarmac, though. No, these roads, for all their ancient status, are not even really roads, more determined cuts through the bush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_guinea-highway.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Guinea highway&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;'The Guinea Highway'. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am attempting to track down Sulaiman Charles, the teacher, but am wondering if this is a wild goose-chase all these hours down this bush track in ‘Zulu One-Five’, our trusty and iconic MSF Landcruiser. Getting battered about hour after hour, rock after rock, river after river. I have learned to trust Ahmet’s driving through these unlikely passages. I made an arrangement with Sulaiman to meet on the road to Kondewakoro over a broken phone conversation more than six hours ago. Sulaiman is an energetic spokesperson, a brilliant teacher with presence and vigour. He is one of my Field Team Leaders, in charge of six Sierra Leone Red Cross volunteers who are methodically surveying the missing, misnamed, and unrepresented villages of the border region for the Post-Ebola Community Rebuild project. Spearheaded by Missing Maps (American Red Cross, MSF, Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team), it is a fundamental vulnerability assessment of at-risk areas where epidemics and natural disasters can run and spread for weeks un-checked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_sulaiman-chiefdoms.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working the map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Working the map (Sulaiman's Chiefdoms). CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are here to correct the map, or more accurately, to leave the capacity for the inhabitants of Toli to map themselves. We have trained four other team leaders like Sulaiman – the best and brightest that the national border regions have to offer. We have also been training a cohort of supervised volunteers. Trained them in the classroom. But this is the bush. And now it is a question of finding them, as they map what can’t be mapped, and we, hampered by the very resistance factors which have prohibited this mapping for so long, are trying to support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_health-centres.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mapping a health centre&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Volunteers putting a health centre on the map in Koinadugu District, aka 'The Land of the Powerful Mixture'. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another chiefdom in the North I came across a border crossing into Guinea made of rickety palm-wood bars. I was reluctant to ‘snap’ the sleepy photogenic border-guard in his vest, standing under the words ‘Immigration’ pencilled on the flaking cement above the ‘office’ doorway. Things can escalate easily here. There are strict security protocols, and the sensitivity of this ‘porous’ borderland domain dictates that we follow strict MSF radio-contact schedules. We are in two-hourly contact with the radio-room in Freetown. A day away. Now, I would like to meet Sulaiman at the border, but we have a lot of ground to cover, and a six o’clock travel curfew to observe. This is no-man’s land. I am aware of the need for caution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_young-biker.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;motorcycle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;On the way to Kondewakoro. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we are with this young biker now, deep in the forest, on the way to Kondewakoro. His chinese-built 125cc road bike has toppled, as he has tried to come up the impossible rocky slope which we, somehow, are attempting to go down. He is laden with six large jerry cans of cow milk, but amazingly there has been no spillage, and we help him re-tie the load. The motorbike is low on its suspension, and the sweating rider is using all his bush-riding skills to snake the bike between the rocks, load and all. But where is Sulaiman? I note that he is young. Young enough to have recently been in school. As we help him get going again, I have a last-minute thought – he might know Sulaiman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Red Cross Motorbike. Sulaiman the teacher. Have you seen him this way?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imperceptibly he nods, and says something. Ahmet interprets a Krio mutter and throw of the head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘He is here. Up ahead.’ A huge grin. Somewhere, down these rocks, through the next river, we will find him. Ahmet is visibly relieved. I knew I could trust Sulaiman, my ‘brother from another mother’, he has called me in the training sessions. But I’m relieved too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘…and is there another road?’ No. No other road. This is the only way to Kondewakoro. We get back into the Landcruiser which flops down the track between the boulders. It doesn’t feel possible yet, but we have somewhere to stay tonight. One hour to go until curfew. No turning back, but now it is certain that we will find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_loaded-motorbike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;How to load a motorbike&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;How to load a motorbike. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And ten minutes later we literally almost run-over Sulaiman on his motorbike. Komba, the isolated volunteer tasked with this spur of the project is interviewing the Village Chief in a clearing. It turns out Komba is a star surveyor, with an amazing grasp of the job in hand. It is difficult to deliver the detailed survey, with its questions about water availability, its carefully crafted cross-referencing of sanitation and disease questions, road conditions and Healthcare access. But it has been worth coming to see how it is done properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_charging-phones.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiring motorbikes to charge phones&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Missing Maps field consultation. Wiring motorbikes to charge phones. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a ‘Loma’ Market here today. It has been a hive of activity. As I look around this village, seemingly thriving in its own right, I can’t help wondering how on earth some of this actual concrete came to be here, given the impossible nature of the only road in. It will be a long time before these villages have convincing vehicular access, despite the fact that they are located on this footpath they call ‘The Guinea Highway’. This track, for better or worse, protects this village in some way, from invasion, but at the same time makes it vulnerable to a changing world around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_broken-crossing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ooops&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ooops. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we photograph wells and water sources, with different surveys, the bigger picture which emerges is the sparsity of consistent water, and the dangerous propensity of water-contamination at source. Villages look well-ordered sometimes, but once surveys start to show exactly how many people actually use the water-sources, how often they dry-up, and how close to latrines (another resource we survey) they can be, the data starts to tell another story; desperate need and hard-boiled living in this disowned and precarious border area. I later geo-photograph two pumps in Kpetema – an ‘India MkII’ and a ‘Bush’ pump. Neither of them dries up in dry season, which makes Kpetema regionally important. We have come across several villages where women are washing in the ford we are crossing, and children carry water from the same river up the hill for drinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_river-water.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ooops&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;River ford. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These communities are susceptible to so much disease from so many quarters. When disaster occurs, their location needs to be traced. Whatever way the locals want it, it needs a name – particularly when some desperate community mobilisation team in the capital receive a dying patient and are trying to pinpoint the place they came from. Local names are important. Geo-tags are critical. Terror spreads as fast as the epidemic itself in these communities, and there are many instances of death resulting from panic as well as actual disease. The enemy is the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_well.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ooops&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the end of the day now, and gaving gathered for council on wooden benches, and sat through typically long-winded introductions with Mami-Queen and Chief, solemn nods were closely followed by furious handshakes (post-Ebola protocol thankfully now permits careful physical contact) and gentle curiosity. Part of the meeting ritual involved the explanation of the corrected name of this village. It moved because of forest fires decades ago, so what I have on my OpenStreetMap, ‘Kekeya’, compiled from old military or colonial data, needs adjusting and renaming. The Chief and the Youth Leader peered curiously over my shoulder as I renamed the village on my phone screen. Approving grunts at me spelling-out the proper village name give way to open-faced enthusiasm and laughing recognition of Chiefdoms and Sub-Chiefdoms so carefully researched by our team and so now available on our own &lt;a href=&quot;http://openmapkit.org/&quot;&gt;OpenMapKit&lt;/a&gt; app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_osm-android.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ooops&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot with my GPS tracks from [OsmAnd](http://osmand.net/) – the everyman SatNav.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has already been established that I am the evangelist in my team, and the people here, perhaps more than a proprietary-thinking western audience, get the publicly owned ethos of our OPEN StreetMap. Our data tools are not concerned with this one-time survey event. Our tools are what you could call ‘culturally scaleable’. They can be used by anyone who understands them, anyone with an android phone, and what we are fundamentally here to do is to spread the word. ‘Communities, map yourselves, on your own terms, [Arguably] before you become mapped by outsiders…’, is our message. This is the OpenSource Global Digital Revolution which can empower the marginalised across cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now the dim shape of the Landcruiser looms in the gloaming as I look out into the village from the out-patient’s waiting bench. Night is falling. Ahmet, my driver, is preparing the Landcruiser for the night. The sound of crickets and other forest insects almost drowns out the quiet African consonants being murmured over food amongst the houses across the track. The cool crescent of the moon is a welcome sight beckoning the forest woodsmoke to rise and meet it. In another part of Africa it has celestial pageantry which I know. I wonder, through the dusk, how they read the stars here. The old navigation envisaged by the new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_night-falling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dusk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Night falls. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall sleep in the mud-built health outpost tonight. The nurse cooks under the palm kitchen roof, and I am sitting, fresh-washed and waiting for what will turn out to be a huge bowl of sweet rice and yoghurt. The pot is simmering on the fire already, gently steaming. I have done ‘Community Entry’. There are rules with village contact here, and society dictates that strangers initially approach the Chief. The performance of this tradition goes back in time, reflecting how outsiders have always been received into these isolated communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20160628_road-signs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dusk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Signage. CC-BY Rupert Allan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later-on I lie under the mosquito net thinking. So: the terrain was too tough for even Zulu One-Five to make it to the border by curfew. Kondewakoro will wait for another time. But it is good to be here, and to have made contact with surveyors on their home territory. Despite the magic of mobile phone network when it is available, Sulaiman has made sure messages are sent through the traditional channels of communication (although drums here, it seems, are a thing of the past). Much as I trust the message of the digital innovation we have come to live by in the west, I know that tomorrow I will meet with Alice and Daniel for motorbike charging instruction and mapping survey technique and evaluation. Without fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comforting village noises have given way to evocative night bush noises, and I drift off to sleep wondering who it was that first surveyed this village all those decades ago…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rupert Allan</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="Field Mapping" /><category term="West Africa" /><category term="Ebola" /><category term="MSF" /><summary>Sierra Leone Red Cross volunteers are methodically surveying the missing, misnamed, and unrepresented villages of the border region for the Post-Ebola Community Rebuild project. Spearheaded by Missing Maps, it is a fundamental vulnerability assessment of at-risk areas where epidemics and natural disasters can run and spread for weeks un-checked.</summary></entry></feed>
